Md Rayed Bin Wahed

https://rayedbinwahed.netlify.app/

rayed.bin.wahed@g.bracu.ac.bd (+880) 1774-882517

Software engineer experienced in Web & Mobile application development and in Machine Learning. Leading a team of engineers to deliver innovative products and improve the Quality of Life of our end customers.

EXPERIENCE

• Therap (BD) Ltd.

Team Lead, Machine Learning

Dhaka, Bangladesh

Oct 2019 - Present

Therap (BD) Ltd. is a wholly-owned subsidiary of **Therap Services LLC.**, **USA**. Therap is a **HIPAA** compliant web and mobile application suite designed to provide comprehensive solutions for the planning, documentation, reporting, and billing needs of organizations supporting people with Intellectual and Developmental Disabilities (IDD).

• Pulse Oximetry Tracking:

- * Build a Progressive Web App using React, GraphQL, and AWS Amplify to track SpO2 and heart-rate of IDD individuals as an early detection mechanism of COVID-19.
- * Send real-time SMS and Email alerts to caregivers if readings reach dangerous levels.

• Face Recognition:

- * Train a Deep Learning model to recognize faces in videos.
- * Blur faces of individuals for whom the viewer does not have access (PHI requirement).
- * The model has an accuracy of 98%.

o Customer Retention:

- * Train a binary classification model to predict the likelihood of customers leaving Therap.
- * Use K-Means clustering algorithm to group customers and extract insight.
- * Implement a feature recommender system to allow greater discovery of services.

o Fall Detection:

- * Train an LSTM model to detect accidental falls from time-series gyroscope and accelerometer smartwatch data.
- * Paired with a real-time notification system, caregivers will be able to respond to injurious events 2x faster.

• Sleep Analysis:

- * Implement comprehensive sleep profiles of IDD individuals using sensor readings from IoT sleep mats.
- * Plot hypnograms, bed in/out statistics, heart and respiration rate diagrams.
- * Inform caregivers of the quality of sleep of patients.

• Cloud Computing:

- * Build robust, scalable Machine Learning pipelines in the cloud.
- * Work with core AWS services such as SageMaker, Lambda, S3, EC2, DynamboDB, IAM, etc.
- * Build serverless workflows, microservices, and implement/consume REST and GraphQL APIs.
- Related Technologies: Python, TensorFlow 2.0, Scikit-Learn, Numpy, Pandas, Plotly, Jupyter Notebooks, Amazon Web Services (AWS), React, GraphQL, Apollo Client, Docker.

• Therap (BD) Ltd.

Full Stack Software Engineer

Dhaka, Bangladesh Oct 2016 - Sep 2019

o Frontend:

- * Implemented interactive frontend components using HTML, CSS, JavaScript and the jQuery library.
- * Optimized client-side code and increased site repsonsiveness by 20%.

o Backend:

- * Collaborated with different teams and end users to understand product requirements and draw up design
- * Implemented core application features using Java, Spring MVC and Hibernate ORM.
- * Wrote unit and integration tests.

o Databases:

- * Worked with Relational Database Management Systems such as Oracle Database and MySQL.
- * Worked with NoSQL databases such as DynamoDB and Cloud Firestore.
- * Wrote highly optimized queries to strore, retrieve large amounts of data.

o Deployment:

- * Deployed applications in a variety of servers and hosting environments such as Oracle Weblogic Server, Node.js, and Netlify.
- * Leveraged build and dependency management tools such as Gradle, Maven, npm, and Yarn in all projects.

• We Are X

Dhaka, Bangladesh

Machine Learning Consultant (Contractual, Remote)

Jan 2019 - Mar 2019

Online social-media customer service platform for large enterprises.

- Task: Implemented a text classification model to classify customer queries written in Bengali and English into 5 categories.
- Outcome: Improved customer service representative productivity by 3x.

EDUCATION

• BRAC University

Dhaka, Bangladesh

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science

Jan 2012 - Aug 2016

- High Distinction: Awarded High Distinction for a Cumulative Grade Point Average (CGPA) of 3.75/4.00.
- Merit Based Scholarship: Awarded Merit Based Scholarship for the duration of the entire program.
- Teaching Assistant: Worked part-time as a TA for Data Structures and Discrete Mathematics.

• Machine Learning Nanodegree

Dhaka, Bangladesh

Udacity

Nov 2019 - Jan 2020

- **Project**: Implemented a Human Activity Recognition (HAR) LSTM Deep Learning model using the WISDM Smartphone and Smartwatch Activity and Biometrics Dataset to classify 5 Activities of Daily Living.
- Outcome: Obtained an accuracy of 90% using only the smartwatch data.

AWARDS AND HONORS

• President's Volunteer Service Award

Washington D.C., USA

President's Council on Service and Civic Participation

Aug 2008

• Recognition: Awarded President's Volunteer Service Award from the President's Council on Service and Civic Participation for outstanding service to community and country.

• YES Leadership Summit

Colorado, USA

 $Sister\ Cities\ International$

Mar 2008

- **Recognition**: Successfully completed the summit consisting of challenging and interactive activities designed to improve leadership skills. Applied those skills in a variety of physically and emotionally demanding situations.
- Youth Exchange and Study (YES) Program

Seattle, USA

Aspect Foundation

Aug 2007 - Sep 2008

• Recognition: One of twenty students from Bangladesh to successfully complete the US Department of State funded YES Program. A humbling experience that prides itself in leadership, cultural values, and acceptance.

• International School Cricket Premier League

Lucknow, India

International Cricket Council

Jan 2011

• Recognition: Represented Bangladesh as a cricketer in the first ever International School Cricket Premier League organized by City Montessori School & Degree College and sponsored by the International Cricket Council (ICC).

• Warren S. Gifford, Ph.D.

Co-author, Driving Tomorrow: Our Roadmap to Sustainable Transportation, Infrastructure and Cities

- o Positions:
 - * President Emeritus, Therap Services LLC.
 - * Former Executive Director in Applied Research, Bell Communications Research
 - $\ast\,$ Former Head of Digital Network Planning Department, Bell Laboratories
 - * Former Special Rapporteur for Digital Network Interfaces in Study Group XVIII in CCITT
- o **Email**: warrensgifford@gmail.com
- \circ **Mobile**: +1 732-673-1475

• David L. Turock, Ph.D.

Director, Biometric Research Laboratory, Therap Services LLC.

 \circ **Email**: david.turock@therapservices.net

 \circ **Mobile**: +1 954-226-9333